A Guide to the Papers of Hiram F. Glazier, 1861 to 1863
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
The Papers of Hiram F. Glazier 1861 to 1863
Special Collections and University Archives, Patricia W. and J. Douglas Perry Library, Old Dominion University
MG 18
One Hollinger Document Case
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open to researchers without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Betty Jones, May 1977
Accession # A77-33
Biographical/Historical Information
Hiram F. Glazier lived in or near, Trenton (Dade County) Georgia just prior to the Civil War, but the exact date and place of his birth are not available. His father was Marnoch Glazier, his mother is not identified in the collection, and his family included three other brothers, Van Glazier, L. Glazier, and X.R. Warren (half brother perhaps), and one or two sisters, Amy Glazier and Ana Marie Glazier. Other known relatives included an uncle, Charles Warren, and two cousins, J.G. Warren and G.W. Butler. In turn, Hiram Glazier married Rebecca Wilson (March 12, 1836-December 8, 1896) and they had three children, Lucy Glazier (September 22, 1856), Marshall Glazier (October 24, 1858), and Belle Glazier (February 24, 1861). Other possible relatives or friends mentioned in this collection include C.H. Chadwick, T.H. Chadwick, Amanda Chadwick, Charles M. Glazier, Mr. Morrison, Franklin Daniel, George Statton, Mrs. M. Kithead (?), Blevins Auston, Mr. Carrel, Hardy Tare, Alexandria Smith, Emerson Blevins, William Buckner and Sis, D.L.G. Wilson, and Mandy.
Mr. Glazier enlisted on July 16, 1861 as a private in Captain G.W. Cureton's company D of the 39th Georgia Regiment. Organized as part of a statewide effort to send a large number of men into battle as quickly as possible, the 39th Georgia volunteers had the following officers: Colonel J.T. McConnell, Lt. Colonel J.F.B. Jackson, Major J.H. Randall, and Adjutant W.M. McCallister. The captains of the various companies were: (A) L.W. Crook, (B) T.H. Pitner, (C) Timothy Ford (D) J.W. Cureton, (E) C.D. Hill (later replaced by Henry P. Osborne), (F) James H. Anderson, (G) B.J. Brown, (H) William H. Edwards, (I) John D. Hayes, (J) J.W. Brady. During the course of the war, this regiment was assigned to the army of Tennessee and saw the following action: the campaign of 1862 in East Tennessee and Kentucky; the battles of the Vicksburg Campaign in Mississippi being among those captured and then later exchanged at Vicksburg; the battle of Missionary Ridge; and the Atlanta and Tennessee campaigns in the spring of 1865. It was consolidated with parts of the Thirty-Fourth and Fifty-Sixth regiments and fought in the campaign of the Carolinas where it surrendered along with J.E. Johnston. Its Colonel, J.T. McConnell, died November 25th, 1864 after being shot in the Battle of Chattanooga and was replaced by Lt. Col. Jackson. In addition, two company commanders died during the course of the war, Captain Brady who was killed in action and Captain Osborne who died at home from an illness contracted earlier.
Hiram Glazier saw extensive action in the war even though he was active for approximately a year. After duty in Big Shanty Cobb County, Georgia and Knoxville and Chattanooga, and perhaps because of several forced marches and an inadequate diet, he became ill and was sent to a hospital outside of Atlanta where he died on May 2, 1862. He was buried in a Confederate cemetery outside that same city.
Scope and Content Information
The papers consist of correspondence including ones Glazier wrote and ones which friends or relatives wrote to him or his family. The papers range in dates from 1861 to 1863. Also, included within them are copies of some interesting and important items including "The Southern Banner" which could be called the Confederate national poem and the response sent to Glazier's widow by T. Calvert of the Confederate Treasury Department. The most important aspect of these papers is the extensive insight that they provide about the attitudes of Confederate soldiers and their families. All of the documents in this collection are copies of the originals.
Contents List
- Correspondence March, 1862 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence April 1, 1862 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence April 7, 1862 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence April 14, 1862 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence April 18, 1862 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, Harry (?) T. (?) January 19, 1861 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence: N.B. Warren July 20, 1861 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 7)
- Correspondence: J.G. Warren September 7, 1861 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence: Van Glazier November 3, 1861 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 9)
- Correspondence: G.W. Butler January 9, 1862 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 10)
- Correspondence: N.B. Warren January 9, 1862 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 11)
- Correspondence: C.H. Chadwick January 19, 1862 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence: T. Calvert April 30, 1863 (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 13)
- "The Southerner's Banner" (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 14)
- Assorted Envelopes (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 15)
- Negative Copies of Collection (Box-folder Box 1, Folder 16)